A Guide to the Papers of Breece D'J Pancake, 1978-1999
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Breece D'J Pancake, 1978-1999
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10975-b
This collection contains ca. 160 items in 1 Hollinger box.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers have been loaned to the University of Virginia Library by John Casey, English Department, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Virginia, on April 29, 1999.
Scope and Content Information
This addition to the papers pertaining to short story writer Breece D' J Pancake (1952-1979) from Milton, West Virginia, ca. 1978-1999, ca. 160 items (1 Hollinger box) consist mainly of the business and literary correspondence of John Casey, acting as Pancake's literary executor. Included in the correspondence folders are letters of his mother Helen Pancake to Casey, post cards from Breece Pancake to John Casey, and letters to John Casey and Helen Pancake (in separate folders) from people interested in the life and writing of Breece Pancake.
Other material in the collection includes contracts; news clippings and printed material; a video cassette recording of a documentary entitled "Breece D'J Pancake: An Appalachian Voice"; articles about Pancake from Dictionary of Literary Biography and Appalachian Journal; royalty statements; three screenplays based on The Stories of Breece D'J Pancake, two by Jeffrey L. Davidson and one by Mark Rance; papers concerning the controversy over a poem reputedly about Pancake published in Appalachian Journal(1998 Summer) and book reviews of A Room Forever The Life, Work, and Letters of Breece D'J Pancake by Thomas E. Douglass (1998) and Trilobites and Other Stories by Breece D'J Pancake (1992).
Contents List
- Articles-"The Apprenticeship of Breece D'J Pancake: An Unpublished Story, Poems, and Letters" 1991 Fall
  With Introduction by Thomas E. Douglass in Appalachian Journal
- Articles-"Breece D'J Pancake (29 June 1952-8 April 1979)" in Dictionary of Literary Biography by Albert E. Wilhem 1992
- Articles-"Bullshit Artist: The Work of Breece D'J Pancake" 1999 Feb
  In C'ville Weekly by Greg Bottoms
- Articles-"Pancake and Benedict" 1988 Spring
  By Bob Snyder in Appalachian Journal
- Articles-"The Story of Breece D'J Pancake" and "Breece D'J Pancake Bibliography" 1990 Summer
  By Thomas E. Douglass in Appalachian Journal
- Book Review 1992, 1998
- Contracts 1983-1992
- Correspondence from Helen Pancake to John Casey 1990-1999, 3 folders
- Correspondence to John Casey re Breece D'J Pancake & His Writing ca. 1990-1999
- Correspondence to Helen Pancake re Breece D'J Pancake & His Writing 1987-1998
- "Hollow the Stories of Breece D'J Pancake" 1991, Typescript of a Screenplay by Mark Rance
- "Hollow" Based on The Stories of Breece D'J Pancake 1991 May 20, Copy of a Typescript of a Screenplay by Jeffrey L. Davidson, Second Draft
- "Hollow" Based on The Stories of Breece D'J Pancake 1992 Apr 15, Typescript of a Screenplay by Jeffrey L. Davidson, Fifth Draft
- News clippings & Printed 1984-1999
- Papers re Controversy over a poem 1998 Jul-Aug
  Re a poem in Appalachian Journal by Victor Depta believed to be about Breece D'J Pancake
- Postcards & Card from Breece D'J Pancake to John Casey 1978 & n.d.
- Royalty Statements for Stories of Breece D'J Pancake 1991-1997
- VHS "An Appalachian Voice" 1987 Jan